<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" []>

<article class="whitepaper" id="Cryptoloop-HOWTO">

<articleinfo>

    <title>COM sobre Cryptoloop</title>

    <author>
        <firstname>Ralf</firstname>
        <surname>H&ouml;lzer</surname>
	<affiliation>
            <address><email>cryptoloop@ralfhoelzer.com</email></address>
        </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>2004-01-15</pubdate>

    <revhistory>
        <revision>
	    <revnumber>1.2</revnumber>
	    <date>2004-03-12</date>
	    <authorinitials>rh</authorinitials>
	    <revremark>S'afig informació sobre dm-crypt, s'actualitza
	    la informació de loop-AES, s'afig més informació sobre
	    seguretat</revremark>
	</revision>
        <revision>
	    <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
	    <date>2004-01-24</date>
	    <authorinitials>rh</authorinitials>
	    <revremark>S'actualitza informació sobre l'aplicació de tapats a util-linux, Loop-AES i Best Crypt</revremark>
	</revision>
        <revision>
	    <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	    <date>2004-01-17</date>
	    <authorinitials>rh</authorinitials>
	    <revremark>Alliberament inicial, revisat per TM at LDP.</revremark>
	</revision>

        <revision>
            <revnumber>v0.9</revnumber>
            <date>2004-01-15</date>
            <authorinitials>rh</authorinitials>
            <revremark>Actualitzat i convertit a DocBook XML.</revremark>
        </revision>

    </revhistory>

    <abstract>
        <para>
        Aquest document explica com crear sistemes de fitxers xifrats
        utilitzant la funcionalitat Cryptoloop. Cryptoloop forma part
        de CryptoAPI a la sèrie 2.6 del nucli Linux.
        </para>
    </abstract>

</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="about">
    <title>Sobre aquest document</title>

        <para>
  Aquest HOWTO descriu com utilitzar el xifrat de dispositiu de bucle
  Cryptoloop a la sèrie 2.6 del nucli Linux. Cryptoloop fa possible la
  creació de sistemes de fitxers xifrats dins d'una partició o d'un
  altre fitxer en el sistema de fitxers. Aquests fitxers xifrats es
  poden moure a un CD, DVD, llàpis de memòria USB, etc. Cryptoloop
  utilitza el dispositiu loop. Aquest és un pseudo-dispositiu que
  serveix com a <quote>bucle</quote> a través del qual ha de passar
  cada crida al sistema de fitxers. D'aquesta manera, les dades poden
  ser processades en ordre per a ser xifrades i desxifrades. Des de la
  versió 2.6, la Crypto API ha sigut integrada dins del nucli
  principal, i crear una sistema de fitxers xifrat és molt més
  fàcil. No es requereixen tapats addicionals. Desgraciadament, la
  utilització de Cryptoloop no està gens ben documentada. Aquest COM
  és un intent de facilitar-li a tothom la creació d'un sistema de
  fitxers xifrat utilitzant la funcionalitat estàndar de Cryptoloop.

  Cryptoloop es basa en la Crypto API del nucli 2.6 de Linux. No hauria
  de confondre's amb Loop-AES, què és un projecte completament
  separat. Cryptoloop és similar a la Crypto API que estava disponible
  com a tapat separat per a la serie 2.4 del nucli. La nova versió no
  és compatible amb l'antiga.
        </para>

<!-- Legal Sections -->
<sect2 id="copyright">
<title>Copyright i Llicència</title>

<para>
This document, <emphasis>Cryptoloop HOWTO</emphasis>,
is copyrighted &copy; 2004 by <emphasis>Ralf H&ouml;lzer</emphasis>.
Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation
License, Version 1.1 or any later version published
by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections,
with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover Texts.
A copy of the license is available at
<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html">
http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds.
</para>
</sect2>


<sect2 id="disclaimer">
<title>Disclaimer</title>
<para>
No liability for the contents of this document can be accepted.
Use the concepts, examples and information at your own risk.
There may be errors and inaccuracies, that could be damaging to
your system.  Proceed with caution, and although this is highly
unlikely, the author(s) do not take any responsibility.
</para>

<para>
All copyrights are held by their by their respective owners,
unless specifically noted otherwise.  Use of a term in this
document should not be regarded as affecting the validity of any
trademark or service mark.  Naming of particular products or
brands should not be seen as endorsements.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="credits">
<title>Crèdits / Col·laboradors</title>

<para>
Voldria agraïr-li a les següents persones què em van ajudar a millorar
aquest COM:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem> 
<para>Dennis Kaledin</para>
</listitem>
<listitem> 
<para>Binh Nguyen</para>
</listitem>
<listitem> 
<para>David Lawyer</para>
</listitem>
<listitem> 
<para>Tabatha Marshall</para>
</listitem>
<listitem> 
<para>Kian Spongsveen</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<!-- Feedback -->
<sect2 id="feedback">
<title>Aportacions</title>
<para>
Les aportacions per a aquest document són realment benvingudes. Envie
les seues addicions, comentaris i crítiques a la següent adreça de
correu: <email>cryptoloop@ralfhoelzer.com</email>.
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="cryptoloop-introduction">
    <title>Introducció</title>
    <para>
    Hi ha algunes alternatives a l'us de Cryptoloop. Loop-AES (<ulink
    url="http://loop-aes.sourceforge.net">http://loop-aes.sourceforge.net</ulink>)
    potser siga la més ben coneguda. Hi proporciona una funcionalitat
    molt similar a Cryptoloop. Aes-loop és actualment més madur que
    Cryptoloop i a més a més és més ràpid (aproximadament el doble de
    ràpid, segons l'autor de loop-AES), perquè utilitza una
    implementació en assemblador de l'AES altament optimitzada. Açò no
    significa que Cryptoloop siga lent. Jo no he notat cap diferència
    significativa de velocitat entre una partició xifrada amb
    Cryptoloop i una sense xifrar en el meu treball diàri amb
    quantitats normals de E/E. Mentre el rendiment d'E/E no siga
    extremadament important per a vostè, Cryptoloop hauria d'anar-li
    bé. Loop-AES ofereix algunes característiques addicionals que
    encara no estàn presents a la implementació de nucli de
    Cryptoloop. Loop-AES requereix eines d'espai d'usuari modificades
    (mount, losetup) i aquestes modificacions són incompatibles amb
    Cryptoloop. Vostè no podrà utilitzar Cryptoloop i Loop-AES alhora.
    </para>
    <para>
    En termes de seguretat, Cryptoloop ho està fent bé. La clau és
    normalment generada a partir d'una contrasenya i la seua suma de
    comprovació (hash) és utilitzada com a clau d'AES. Açò condueix a
    la possibilitat d'un <ulink
    url="http://lwn.net/Articles/67216/">known-plaintext
    attack</ulink>.  Loop-AES és superior en aquesta questió, perquè
    genera una clau aleatòria i xifra la clau separadament, fent que
    un atac known-plaintext siga molt més difícil. Loop-AES també
    suporta un mode multi-clau, on els sectors són xifrats amb 64
    claus AES diferents. Generalment, un atac de força bruta sobre la
    seua contrasenya pot resultar molt efectiu, si vostè tria una
    contrasenya dèbil. Per a estar en la banda segura, la seua
    contrasenya hauria de tindre almenys 20 caràcters de
    longitud. D'una altra manera un atac de força bruta sobre la
    contrasenya seria molt més senzill que intentar un atac de força
    bruta sobre el xifrat AES directament.
    </para>
    <para>
    La funcionalitatat Cryptoloop al nucli estàndard proporciona una
    implementació neta i estable sense necessitat de tapats
    addicionals. Com que és bastant nou, podria no haver rebut la
    quantitat necessària de revisions en termes de seguretat. Vostè
    mateix ha de decidir què s'ajusta a les seues necessitats.
    </para>
    <para>
    IMPORTANT: Cryptoloop ha estat marcat com a deprecated en el
    darrer nucli 2.6. Això significa que ja no es seguirà mantenint
    activament. El successo de Cryptoloop serà <ulink
    url="http://www.saout.de/misc/dm-crypt/">dm-crypt</ulink>. Dm-crypt
    està disponible en el nucli des de la versió 2.6.4. Cryptoloop
    estarà disponible en el nucli principal durant un llarg període de
    temps, però dm-crypt serà el mètode a escollir per al xifrat en el
    futur. Dm-crypt està basat en el mapejador de disposiius i ofereix
    bàsicament la mateixa funcionalitat que Cryptoloop. Encara és
    bastant nou i no encara no hi han eines d'usuari fàcils
    d'utilitzar. Es considera Dm-crypt té un codi molt més net que
    Cryptoloop, però hi ha algunes diferències importants. Per
    exemple, la creació d'un sistema de fitxers xifrat al llarg d'un
    fitxer encara requereix travessar un dispositiu de bucle, però
    aquest suport encara està en desenvolupament.
    </para>
    <para>
    Hi han altres eines que li permeten crear un sistema de
    fitxers. BestCrypt és un producte comercial de Jetico. Li permet
    crear contenidors xifrats i disposa d'una gran quantitat de
    xifradors per a triar. També ofereix algunes característiques It also offers some nifty features such as
    hidden containers. It is available for Windows and Linux, which
    makes it suitable for interchanging encrypted containers between
    Windows and Linux. BestCrypt now compiles on 2.6 kernels as
    well. Cryptoloop can also create containers that can be moved
    around, by creating the encrypted file system within a file as
    described below. I don't know of a way to access the
    Cryptoloop-encrypted files from other operating systems such as
    Windows. In this case, BestCrypt may be your only choice.
    </para>
    <para>
    There are other commercial disk encryption tools such as PGP disk, but to my knowledge there is no Linux support for them.
    </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="kernel-configuration">
    <title>Configuring the kernel</title>
    <para>
    In order to use Cryptoloop, you need to activate a few kernel options. You have the option to either compile these
    requirements as modules or compile them directly into the kernel. The following steps enable them as modules.
    If you are not familiar with building a 2.6 kernel, you should refer to the <ulink url="http://www.linuxdocs.org/HOWTOs/Kernel-HOWTO.html">Linux Kernel HOWTO</ulink>. The following
    instructions just give the minimal steps.
    </para>

<orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>Go to the directory that holds your kernel source tree (usually <filename>/usr/src/linux/</filename>) and start the configuration:</para>
	<screen>make menuconfig</screen>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Enable general loop device support. Active <quote>Loopback device support</quote> under:</para>
	<screen>Device Drivers -> Block Devices -> Loopback device support</screen>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Enable Cryptoloop support in the same section. The option should show up as soon as you enable general loopback support.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Enable the cryptographic API by going to <quote>Cryptographic options</quote> from the main menu. You can safely enable most algorithms here.  I would recommend that you enable the following:</para>

	<screen>
    -- Cryptographic API
     &lt;*&gt;   HMAC support  
     &lt; &gt;   Null algorithms
     &lt;*&gt;   MD4 digest algorithm
     &lt;*&gt;   MD5 digest algorithm
     &lt;*&gt;   SHA1 digest algorithm
     &lt;*&gt;   SHA256 digest algorithm
     &lt;*&gt;   SHA384 and SHA512 digest algorithms
     &lt;*&gt;   DES and Triple DES EDE cipher algorithms
     &lt;*&gt;   Blowfish cipher algorithm
     &lt;*&gt;   Twofish cipher algorithm
     &lt;*&gt;   Serpent cipher algorithm 
     &lt;*&gt;   AES cipher algorithms
     &lt;*&gt;   CAST5 (CAST-128) cipher algorithm
     &lt;*&gt;   CAST6 (CAST-256) cipher algorithm 
     &lt;*&gt;   Deflate compression algorithm
     &lt; &gt;   Testing module
        </screen>

	<para>
    If you decide to make them as modules, make sure you load the appropriate modules (cryptoloop, aes, etc.) at startup before you continue.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Make your kernel and modules and install them. For example, if you are using lilo on a x86 machine, this can be done like this:</para>

	<screen>
     make
     make modules_install
     cp arch/i386/boot/bzImage /boot/kernel-2.6.1
     lilo
        </screen>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Load the required modules at startup. This is handled differently on the various distributions. For example, on Gentoo these modules can be added to <filename>/etc/modules.autoload/kernel-2.6</filename>. If you have compiled Cryptoloop as a module, it will have to be loaded first. It will automatically load the basic loop device module as well. You can manually load the module with:</para>

	<screen>modprobe cryptoloop</screen>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
</sect1>


<sect1 id="userspace-tools">
    <title>Getting the user space tools</title>

    <para>
    The Cryptoloop driver requires updated userspace tools to actually create and mount the encrypted
    file system. An updated util-linux package is needed and can be obtained from <ulink url="http://ftp.cwi.nl/aeb/util-linux/util-linux-2.12.tar.gz">http://ftp.cwi.nl/aeb/util-linux/util-linux-2.12.tar.gz</ulink>.
    The most current version is 2.12. There will be new versions out soon that will probably introduce major changes, so make sure you check this
    HOWTO for updates before upgrading to a newer version.
    Unfortunately there are many patches for util-linux out there. There are differences in the way how encrypted partitions are created
    and mounted. In order to use util-linux 2.12 with a 2.6 kernel at least the following two patches need to be applied:
    <orderedlist>
    
    <listitem><ulink url="http://www.stwing.org/~sluskyb/util-linux/losetup-combined.patch">Combined losetup patch</ulink></listitem>
    <listitem><ulink url="http://www.ece.cmu.edu/~rholzer/cryptoloop/util-linux-2.12-kernel-2.6.patch">Util-linux 2.6 patch</ulink></listitem>

    </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
    Download the util-linux package and the two patches above.
    First extract the util-linux package and then apply the two patches:
    </para>
    <screen>
     tar xvfz util-linux-2.12.tar.gz

     cd util-linux-2.12

     patch -p1 < /path_to_patchfile/losetup-combined.patch

     patch -p1 < /path_to_patchfile/util-linux-2.12-kernel-2.6.patch
     </screen>
    <para>
    After applying the patches, compile and install util-linux according to the instructions in the INSTALL file.
    </para>


    <para>
    I recommend to use <ulink url="http://gentoo.org">Gentoo Linux</ulink>, which automatically applies these patches when emerging the util-linux patches.
    Other distributions may have versions of util-linux available, that have these patches aleady applied as well.
    
    </para>
 
</sect1>


<sect1 id="loopdevice-setup">
    <title>Setting up the loop device</title>

<para>Cryptoloop can be used either on a file or an entire file system. The following describes how to
set it up on a particular partition. This partition can be any partition you like; the following
example uses <filename>/dev/sda1</filename>. I have chosen to use AES as a cipher, but you can substitute any cipher
you like that has been enabled in the kernel. You can get a list of the algorithms supported by
your currently running kernel by looking into <filename>/proc/crypto</filename>. An excellent resource, discussing the
different cryptographic algorithms, are Bruce Schneier's books, Applied Cryptography and Practical
Cryptography. Both AES and Serpent are probably a reasonable choice. AES has been cryptanalyzed a lot
and no serious weaknesses have been discovered so far. Serpent has not been analyzed as much, but is
considered to be even a little bit stronger than AES. However, Serpent is also slower than AES.
Stay away from DES, it is both slow and weak. Triple-DES may be an option, but AES is probably more
secure and faster, so there is really no reason to use Triple-DES anymore.
</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>It is recommended that you format your partition and fill it with random data before you create the encrypted file system on it. This will make it harder for an attacker to detect patterns in your encrypted partition.
</para>

	<para><emphasis>WARNING!</emphasis> </para>

	<para>Be careful what you type here for your partition. If you do make a mistake, you can easily overwrite the wrong partition with random garbage! </para>

	<para>Filling a partition with random data can be done as follows:</para>

<screen>dd if=/dev/urandom of=/dev/sda1 bs=1M
</screen>

<para>You may get an error message that the device is full. You can ignore it.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Select a cipher and key size. A list of ciphers supported by your kernel can be obtained from <filename>/proc/crypto</filename>. I recommend that you use AES with a 256-bit key.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Set up the loop device. This is done using the <command>losetup</command> command from the util-linux package. The following command creates an encrypted filesystem using the loop device 0 using the AES cipher with a 256-bit key on the device <filename>/dev/sda1</filename>:</para>

<screen>losetup -e aes-256 /dev/loop0 /dev/sda1
</screen>

        <para>The command prompts for a password. Select a strong password and try to remember it without having to stick a Post-It note to your monitor. 
        There is one big downside to using Cryptoloop. Since the password is hashed to create the encryption key, it is not easy to change the password later on. 
        The most straight-forward way of changing the password is to create a new encrypted partition or file and move all data into it. For this reason, make 
        sure you select a strong password from the start.  AES may be a strong algorithm, but if you chose a weak password, that security goes down the drain.
        </para>
        <para>If <command>losetup</command> fails with an INVALID ARGUMENT error message, there is a problem with your util-linux package. 
         Make sure you have followed the instructions above on how to install a patched version of util-linux. Older and unpatched version use a 
         different way of passing the key size, and do not work with the 2.6 Crypto API.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Create a file system. You can chose whatever file system you like. The following creates an ext3 file system using the loop device:</para>

<screen>mkfs.ext3 /dev/loop0
</screen>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Mount the encrypted file system. First you need to create a mount point, such as <filename>/mnt/crypto</filename>:</para>

<screen>mkdir /mnt/crypto</screen>

	<para>Then you need to mount the file system. At this stage you need to tell mount explicitly which loop device to use:</para>

<screen>mount -t ext3 /dev/loop0 /mnt/crypto
</screen>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>You can now play with your encrypted file system until you are bored.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Unmount the file system. After you are done playing, unmount the filesystem:</para>

<screen>umount /mnt/crypto</screen>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Detach the loop device. The loop device is still attached to your partition. Detach it with:</para>

<screen>losetup -d /dev/loop0</screen>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
</sect1>


<sect1 id="mounting-filesystem">
    <title>Mounting the encrypted file system</title>

<para>
For all operations on the Cryptoloop device, it is important that the necessary modules are loaded. You
need to load at least the Cryptoloop module and the modules for each cipher with <command>modprobe</command>. If the features
are compiled directly into the kernel, this is not necessary.
</para>

<para>In order to mount the encrypted file system created above, you can use the standard mount command
from util-linux:
</para>

<screen>mount -t ext3 /dev/sda1 /mnt/crypto/ -oencryption=aes-256</screen>


<para>You will be prompted for the password and the file system will be mounted just as any other. Since the encryption option
implies that this is a Cryptoloop filesystem, it will automatically pick an available loopback device.
</para>

<para>When you are done, unmount it with:
</para>

<screen>umount /mnt/crypto</screen>

<para>You can add the following line to <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>:
</para>

<screen>/dev/sda1               /mnt/crypto     ext3            noauto,encryption=aes-256       0 0</screen>

<para>Now you can simply mount the device with:
</para>

<screen>mount /mnt/crypto</screen>

<para>That's it. Have fun.</para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="filebased">
<title>Using a file instead of a partition</title>

<para>
It is just as easy to create an encrypted file system within a file on another file system. This is especially useful
if you want to back up this file by burning it to a DVD, etc. You can then easily move the file around to other
machines as well.
</para>

<para>To initially create a 100MB file containing random data use the following command:
</para>

<screen>dd if=/dev/urandom of=/mystuff.aes bs=1k count=100000</screen>

<para>
If you want to change the size of the file, change the <varname>count</varname> value accordingly. The above command creates 100000 blocks
of 1k in size, but you can change this to whatever you like. Just make sure it is not too small to hold the file system you
chose. You can choose any file name and path you want instead of <filename>/mystuff.aes</filename> as long as there's enough space on the partition.
</para>

<para>You can then create the encrypted file system within this file, similar to the way it is done above:
</para>

<screen>losetup -e aes-256 /dev/loop0 /mystuff.aes</screen>

<para>Now you can create the file system:</para>

<screen>
mkfs.ext3 /dev/loop0
</screen>

<para>
and mount it:
</para>

<screen>
mount -t ext3 /dev/loop0 /mnt/crypto
</screen>

<para>
Finally, unmount and detach the loop device:
</para>

<screen>
umount /mnt/crypto
losetup -d /dev/loop0
</screen>

<para>
You can then mount the file system later on as follows:
</para>

<screen>mount /mystuff.aes /mnt/crypto -oencryption=aes-256</screen>

<para>If you want to move the file or burn it to a CD or DVD, make sure you <command>unmount</command> it first.
</para>

</sect1>



</article>


